[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
[Music]
welcome everyone to the store
the stowaway is a digital campfire where
we cohere
and dialogue about what matters most at
the knife's edge of what's happening now
i'm your host dave mcfadyen and i'm
really excited to introduce howard bloom
to the store
howard has been one of my favorite
authors since i read his book the
lucifer principle back in the 90s
it remains one of my most influential
books i've ever read
i just discovered the field of mimetics
at the time
so the the study of memes or mind
viruses
and the lucifer principle was about how
memes turn
individual humans into super organisms
and how they compete for
power and influence and resources
so it's not really a stretch to identify
superorganisms with cultures and these
conflicts with wars
which means that howard was writing
about the culture wars way before it was
cool
uh since then uh so the lucifer
principle was just the first
of many books that he wrote to develop
his theory of mass behavior so following
the lucifer principle there was a god
problem
which talks about the birth of the first
atoms and then global brain explains the
evolution of multicellular beings
and the genius of the beast a radical
revision of capitalism is about the form
of mass behavior that we call the
economy
about the exuberant mass creativity we
call western civilization
his most recent two books were more
autobiographical in nature i noticed
one about how howard accidentally
invented the 60s by being involved in
the early hippie movement
and all this time but great up until
then i kind of viewed howard as
a scientist so when i read einstein
michael jackson me i was really blown
away by his
amazing career in music like uh
just reading some of the icons that he
worked with
he was involved as a publicist for
prince michael jackson bob marley bette
midler billy joel
paul simon billy idol peter gabriel
david byrne
john mellencamp queen kiss aerosmith ac
dc
and of course uh joan jett who wrote the
forward to his book
and that's who we were listening to when
you all came in
and just last year howard was the
subject of a documentary so i just want
to play the the trailer for that to give
you
an idea of who we get to talk to tonight
so if you get
give me a second to share my screen
give me another second to let some more
people in
all right give me a thumbs up if you can
see the screen
on tonight's show you'll meet an
extraordinary character in the 1980s
howard bloom was the top publicist in
the music industry with clients like
joan jett
michael jackson and helped princess
get going here in new york and it would
be like one
after another a howard boom client
would have a number one record
his career was legendary but in 1988
howard fell ill with chronic fatigue
syndrome
and has been bedridden ever since
despite his illness bloom typed out the
scientific theories he'd been thinking
about his entire life
[Music]
power shows how nature sharpens its
scalpel can make uh
rootier beams
basically howard was ahead of the car
i could try to convince you that howard
bloom is next on a very short list that
includes darwin
einstein and buckminster fuller and how
he's going to change the way we see
ourselves and everything around us
but howard can probably do a much better
job of convincing you himself
so this is called the grand unified
theory of everything in the universe
including the human soul
what does the hypothalamus do what
scientists repress
masculinity in sexless lizards there are
over 9000
of these chapters the stuff that keeps
it all together the glue is in here and
once i'm gone that glue is gone
[Music]
[Applause]
meanwhile
all right
we're back so welcome howard
welcome to the store thanks david david
by the way is my i've always regarded
him as my cyber patron
ever since something like 1995.
it's been my pleasure um
so uh you've written about
like the birth of the universe right
from the big bang
um the evolution of life uh what
does this have to do with the search for
this
human soul in the power pits of rock and
roll what is here
grand unified theory well the search for
the gods within okay let me give it to
you biographic autobiographically
um when i was 10 years old absolutely
nobody wanted me and i think my hometown
of buffalo new york other kids wanted to
have nothing to do with me
and my parents didn't seem to have
anything to do with me either
so one day you know how you know the
location of every book
in your parents house because the books
never move from their positions on the
shelves
one day a book i had never seen appeared
in my lap
and um i opened it
and it said the first two rules of
science are these the truth in any price
including the price of your life and it
mangled the story of galileo
it told it as if galileo had been
willing to go to the stake in order to
defend his truth
that turned out to be wrong but i needed
the heroic version of the story at the
time
so i'm glad i told it wrong and uh the
second rule of science
says is look at things right under your
nose as if you've never seen them before
and then proceed from there look for
things that everybody that around you
take for granted and you take for
granted too
things that are invisible to you and
bring them into the realm of visibility
and it gave the example of anton von
loenhoek who invented the microscope
and looked at pond water and discovered
it was filled with an entire realm
of animals with which we've shared this
planet for as long as we've been around
um invisible microscopic or
well more microorganisms he called them
animal cules
um and all of a sudden i had
a religion those first two rules
and all of a sudden i had companions
people like galileo
anton van loon and hope men who could
not reject me the way the kids did the
way my parents did for a very simple
reason
they'd been dead for 350 years um
i started reading two books a day
science and science fiction one book
under the
desk at school another book when i got
home at night
and then i had a peculiar experience
first of all one of the things
that i derived from those books that the
books seem to be saying to me
is that science is about the aspiration
toward omniscience
um there is no god there is no
omniscient being
but omniscience is an aspiration that
exists in us
and as science people it is our job to
look at even the most
overlooked phenomena and to bring them
into the world of science
so when i was 12 i realized
probably after reading bertrand russell
that i was an atheist
but i kept that idea out of the
mainstream of my mind
hidden away in a little closet because i
had the first party i was ever going to
be invited to in buffalo new york coming
up
it was my bar mitzvah and there were
going to be presents
so i did the bar mitzvah
um the rabbi called me the voice which
was very sweet of him
um i spent two months writing thank you
notes to all the people who had sent me
presents the stash of presents was
enormous
and then in september i was finally free
to call myself an atheist but there was
one small problem in the jewish calendar
september is
very important because the high holidays
the most important
days of the jewish year take place in
september
now my parents were not religious my
parents were not
observant they very seldom went to a
synagogue unless a friend's kid was
having a bar mitzvah
but when it came to the high holidays
there was a ferocity
in their desire to get me to the
synagogue whether i was an atheist or
not
so they got me in a suit i don't know
how they did that i hate suits
they got me into their blue four-door
fraser automobile i don't know how they
accomplished that
either they drove me all the way to
richmond avenue where the synagogue was
and i refused to go any further
so i'm holding on to the door frame of
this
sturdily american-made car and my
parents are
yanking at my socks literally trying to
drag me up the street like a sack of me
and something hits me galileo made his
discoveries by taking a brand new
instrument that had been
developed for military purposes a tube
with a lens on
this end and a lens on that end um it
was used for looking over the horizon so
you see the troops of the spanish
it was developed in holland so holland's
arch enemies were the spanish
and this was developed so you could see
the spanish long before
they realized you had seen them um
galileo had the audacity to take this
instrument that was designed for
horizontal viewing
and to turn it up at the sky this was
outrageous everybody knew
what was in the heavens
that's god's underwear that's the
underside of god's living room rug you
do not keeping tom god
plus god is perfect and aristotle told
us that the perfect form
is the sphere or the circle so obviously
everything up there had to be spheres
and circles
galileo did the outrageous he lifted his
telescope and pointed it at the sky and
saw that there were a bunch of rocks up
there pock marked imperfect
rocks and thus began a total
redefinition of our relationship to the
cosmos
um anton von luenhoek took his lens
which he used for horizontal viewing
to look at fabrics he was a draper and
he looked at the fabrics he was
importing from all over the world to see
how fine weave was
and instead of pointing that um
horizontally the way he
normally did he pointed it down and he
discovered the entire
micro world and i realized as my parents
were trying to drag their firstborn up
the street
um hamburgering my face on the sidewalk
um that there were gods in this picture
um there are no gods of the heaven there
are no gods under the earth
but there were gods inside the passion
with once my
parents were absolutely determined to
drag me to the synagogue
and if there are gods inside my parents
then there are gods
inside of me now look science
is about the aspiration to omniscience
the second rule of science is look at
things right under your nose as if
you've never seen them before
especially the things that other people
overlook and take for granted
and all of a sudden i was confronted
with
the emotions we call divinity um
i was confronted with the ecstatic
emotions that appear in scientific
ritual i mean in uh in uh
religious rituals and because the
aspiration of sciences omniscience i
wanted to understand these things
scientifically not just scientifically
there's a term i wouldn't discovered
until
many many decades later from
uh robin fox who founded the
anthropology department at
uh at rutgers university it's called
participant observer science
i wanted to be able to dive into the
experience and experience the ecstatic
experience that sense of being lifted up
to something much higher than yourself
and simultaneously i wanted to come to
understand it in scientific terms
meanwhile um when i was 12 my
public high schools the public high
school was a nightmare for me
it felt like a giant prison and my
parents uh offered to send me
to a uh a private high school
and but they heard i've been reading two
books a day which means i paid no
attention in class for years
and my parents said look if we send you
to this place you have to promise us
you're going to work um that you're
going to work hard
so i took that promise very seriously
and i started working my tail off
meanwhile the kids at my school
hated me so you know the most popular
kid in class gets to be class president
the second most popular kid gets to be
class vice president
most popular jew gets to be treasurer
and the most popular girl gets to be
secretary i had no chance of achieving
any of those positions
but we had functional committees that
had to get
things done and kids who are popular
don't like to get things done they like
to get things
solely on the ability of their looks and
their charm
so when it came to the program committee
i was voted the head of the program
committee two years in a row now what's
the program committee the program
committee
you have five school assemblies a school
assembly at the first 45 minutes that
you arrive in the school
every single day um i got to program two
of those
and i got to emcee five of them and one
day the
the juniors um came to me
and they said we're having a dance could
you advertise it for us no they didn't
realize the absurdity of this request
if there was a dance or a party anywhere
in buffalo new york my hometown
i was cordially invited to stay as far
away as possible preferably cleveland or
austin texas
um nonetheless they wanted me to
advertise to their dance
so i put a record on a turntable i went
on stage i was by now accustomed to
appearing in front of 350 people
every single day and something really
weird happened
i can't dance i can't do the box step i
can't do the fox trot i can't do the
waltz i can't do any of them
um i started free-forming and apparently
i was free-forming in a way that no one
in that room had ever seen before it was
like a looney tune drew on
on a night when chuck jones the creator
of the looney tunes
had dropped lsd and i saw
the face of the girl who loathed me the
most i saw her
eyes widening i saw her pupils dilated
i saw her face melting i saw all the 349
other people's faces melting at the same
time
i saw them melting into one giant
communal blob of energy
i saw that amoebic blob of energy reach
the pseudopod out to me
and send the energy of 350 people
through me as if i were an empty pipe
i had an out-of-body experience i was on
the ceiling
watching all of this take place and i
saw that energy go up around
some place around my head become utterly
transmogrified and flow back to that
audience
and when i finished when the song was
over three and a half minutes later
the audience did something it looked
like it had practiced
all its life it was so good at it but it
had never done in my time at that school
not for homecoming queens
not for football heroes not for
returning foreign students from italy
um it surged down to the foot of the
stage
it picked me up on its shoulders and it
carried me out of the auditorium and
carried me carried me all the way up the
walkway to the building
where we had classes so all of a sudden
the the ecstatic experience that i had
been pursuing
for scientific purposes and personal
purposes since i was 12 years old
had hit me over the head and carried me
utterly away
and it became my key to understanding
people like michael jackson prince bob
marley bette midler etc
meanwhile back when i was 12 and my
parents sent me for an
interview with the headmaster of this
school
um
i walked into his office and i said i
will only come to your school on the
following terms and i
said first you have to teach me russian
because russia is going to be important
country
in the next few decades secondly you
have to
reverse the order with which you teach
me your science courses right now
you teach biology versus chemistry
second
and you teach biology no you teach
biology first
chemistry second and physics third
you have to reverse that order i want
physics first
so that you would teach me the origins
of the first elementary
particles teach me about the big bang by
the way the big bang was extremely
controversial
at that point um fred hoyle the guy who
was behind steady state theory of the
universe thought that that was the year
he would knock big bang out of existence
forever um big bang theory
so i want you to teach me physics you
teach me the big bang and the origin of
the first particles
i want you to teach me chemistry so that
you teach me
what happens when atoms form and when
those atoms get together in
social groups i want you to teach me
biology third because that
you have to teach me what happens when
molecules get together in
mega molecules and achieve the ability
to reproduce and the ability to make
life
then i want you to teach me anthropology
so that we get to the origin of the
first human societies
then i want you to teach me history and
surprisingly he said yes but this was
the beginning of laying out a timeline
a timeline of the universe a timeline of
the universe that would join
everything from the big bang to what's
going on in your brains as we are having
this
conversation tonight that
does cover you david you left out a book
the muhammad code
how it has a prophet isis al-qaeda and
boko haram
what do all of these books have in
common yes the god problem
talks about the origins of the universe
and something i call corollary
generator theory a theory of how the
universe unfolds
um and the lucifer principle
talks about the biological origins of
evil um and the genius of the beast
talks about matt the master
let me go back a second i have told
people for many years trying to capture
what the hell it is that i do
that my field is mass behavior from the
mass behavior of quarks
to the mass behavior of human beings
well
the muhammad code is one of the most
astonishing manifestations of group
behavior
in the history of this planet it
fashioned a religion that gained an
empire seven times the size
or or eleven times the size of the
conquest of alexandria the great
five times the size of the roman empire
and seven times the size of the united
states
nothing else like it has ever happened
if you don't understand
it you don't understand mass behavior um
and the genius of the beast was about um
economies economies are an extraordinary
form of mass behavior that show
primal patterns that you've been traced
all the way back to bacteria
and if you choose you can prove that you
can trace those patterns back to the
formation
of the first galaxies so what
is the grand unified theory of
everything in the universe including
sex violence in the human soul it is
based on that timeline approach
that puts everything from the ecstasies
of saint teresa
and the poetry of t.s eliot
to the big bang the origin of the first
quarks the origin of the first galaxy is
the origin of the first stars
the origin of the first uh atoms
and the origin of the first nuclear or
the first um
molecules all the way up to what's going
on right now and it has certain basic
principles one of them
is this is a cosmos of the super size
surprise
at every step in this cosmos life its
products have been she has used them as
antennae
to feel out her next possibility and her
next possibility has always been subtle
something utterly unpredictable by air
since healing logic
for example at 300 000 abb
300 000 years after the big bang up
until that point the universe had been a
plasma
which means that particles were moving
at super speed they were
bouncing into each other head on like
bullets colliding bouncing off of each
other
and then colliding at bullet speed with
another particle
almost immediately um it had been what
donald trump likes to call a mess
although it was an organized mess but
we'll leave that form of organization
for
later um 300 000 to 380 000 abb
the universe slowed down it cooled down
and particles did
something absolutely extraordinary
particles that were relatively speaking
the size of the empire state building
discovered
they had an inanimate longing particles
relatively speaking the size of your
fist
discovered they had an inanimate longing
that these two
with an 1800 times difference in size
between them
should ever get together in any way
was the most absurd thought on planet
earth
or long before planet earth um
and you got these tiny things discovered
there in an inanimate long
perfectly fit the inanimate lung of the
things relatively speaking the size of
empire state buildings
the things relative to speaking the size
of empire state buildings
were protons the things relatively
speaking the size of your fist
were electrons now here's where the
super-sized surprise
comes in i mean it is utterly
shocking that these two should have a
social relationship and once they
discover it that they should discover
basically atomic shells the electrons
should move
only within very defined shells
and in fact could not move in between
themselves and the nucleus
or they could not move straight out of
the shell
to get anywhere there had to be a shell
above them and they had to
disappear on shell number one and
reappear on channel number two
you would think all of that was enough
of a super-sized surprise no
it's not when you combine these two
elementary particles according to
aristotelian logic garbage in garbage
out
you've got two particles that's all
you've got
and yet when you put these two particles
together not only did you get the
properties
called an atom you got the properties
of hydrogen and helium you got
atoms atoms and
and the properties of hydrogen and
helium are completely
unpredictable from knowing the basics
of a proton and an electron
now here's where the supersized surprise
comes in
um according to aristotle if you break
things down to their smallest parts
particles and you understand the laws
um with which they operate you
understand everything you can explain
everything no i'm sorry when you put
social aggregations together
whether they're three quarks forming
either a proton or a neutron
a proton getting together with an
electron
astonishing and totally unpredictable
properties emerge we call them emergent
properties i call them the super precise
surprise
and you can trace these super sized
surprises at every step of the
universe's evolution
right on up to what we are doing now
right now all of us in this room
are feelers we are antennae for a cosmo
searching out her next super-sized
surprise and that's
a a tiny condensation
of the grand unified theory of
everything in the universe including sex
violence in the human soul
that is a lot to process um
so i've noticed that you often use
religious language
in your your books you talk about the
gods within you've mentioned divinity
and soul of course is the subtitle of
your latest book
um as a scientist how do you understand
these terms
um that's a good question because as a
scientist
it is hard look you have certain
sciences where you could define your
terms in advance
um but the reality of science is you're
feeling out things that are unknown
and right now soul and the gods within
are unknown now
back when i was uh 14 years old i had
been
as you know utterly fascinated by the
gods within us
for two years and then i heard that
there was a book called the varieties of
the religious experience
by william james now we didn't have
amazon in those days and
buffalo was not exactly a book rich town
but i went on a hunt
for that book and i finally found it at
the university of buffalo bookstore
and it was as if william james had
laid out a bunch of these ecstatic
experiences
on a lab bench and said directly to me
in 1902 i do not have the tools with
which to understand these things
but you're coming along in the 1950s and
1960s
and you will have the tools
with which to understand these things
but he left me well he gave examples of
people like george fox
who saw blood raining down from the sky
and gushing through the streets
of litchfield he gave the example of um
of theresa saint teresa who was a nun
alone in a stone a dark stone cell
at night and she felt angels penetrate
the walls
and push uh spears
into her entrails and that push gave her
ecstasies beyond belief
and she felt that in the arms of those
angels in the arms of christ himself
that she soared over the landscape of
the world
and she was filled with the love of god
that is beyond
uh the powers of description well you
know that at the age of 16 i
had one of those experiences william
james did say this
he said every one of the experiences
that i've described to you as a
psychopathology
yet in the hands of certain people
psychopathologies
can become the engines of history
so with my scientific tools i had
started in microbiology and theoretical
physics i had my
first meeting with the head of the
graduate physics department at the
university of buffalo
when i was 12 we discussed big bangers
to steady state degree of the universe
and the interpretation of the doppler
shift and he came out of his office and
put his hand
on my shoulder and said to my mom you
don't have to save for grad school for
him
he'll get fellowships and theoretical
physics at any school he wants
but i knew those tools had to be applied
to one of the most obvious things
under our noses and behind our noses the
gods within
to our emotions um to our passions
and so i've been on the track of joining
these things together
they are in the same universe david and
they're in the same universe
for a reason if we don't understand
things like consciousness
and human passion and the gods within us
our understanding even of the big bang
and its first elementary particles
is going to be missing something big and
in fact it is something too big
because we take the er sicilian approach
of breaking things down to their
smallest elements
and understanding them we fail to
understand the emergent properties
and those are the really big deal we
fail
to understand the super-sized surprises
not only can't we predict them we don't
even recognize that they exist
which means our science is a primitive
level like the level of the old
lawn stone kit stone toolkit with which
humans began hacking
up animals 3.1 million years ago it's
time for us
to get a science that also can
comprehend the super-sized surprise
and one of those super size surprises is
whatever the hell it is
that the ecstatic experience the sense
of being caught up in something larger
than yourself
the experience that i described on stage
at the park school of buffalo
the experiences of that kind that hit
michael jackson
that hit prince that hit john mellencamp
that hit my artist and were the core
of their art the connective tissue
that welded them to their audience
if we don't understand those mysteries
we don't really understand this cosmos
we are still in science 101.
right um yeah i understand that
the the things that you're referencing
with religious
language are real they're significant
they're important they're
emergent properties i just wonder if you
think they're
the same things that religious people
are talking about when they use the same
words
well they they couch it in a different
world view
in their world view there is a god
in their worldview there is a heaven
and a hell in my worldview because i'm
an atheist
uh a secular humanist is what i guess
you could call me
um there is no god and the trick is to
explain these things without a god
um because they are real as you said
they are real
if you you need to understand how
passion
affects humans and coagulates them in
groups
if you're going to understand the rise
of
islamic civilization and that's an
extremely important part of human
history
or what's going on in this election in
the united states
at this minute
and science is about the aspiration
toward omniscience
so science has to grab everything
and try both to experience it and
explain it
right um just want to mention
that if anyone wants to ask a question
to howard um
feel free to drop questions in the chat
um prefix a question with a keyword
question um help me find them if you'd
like a question you can upload it with a
plus one
if you don't want to ask the question
yourself
uh just indicate that in the chat as
well otherwise
i'll ask you to unmute yourself to ask
the question
and somebody asked what's the next super
size surprise
i saw that come up on my screen that's
right okay
um yeah let's go with that rob would you
like to ask a question please
sure yeah so i imagine that based on
your definition of a super-sized
surprise it
might be a little hard to answer but uh
but
at least would what domain would it
appear in uh
you know would it be an emergent
property of human social interactions or
a property of our technological systems
could you make any predictions about its
attributes
um i think it does remember we humans
like every species that ever existed
are antennae feelers for a cosmos
feeling out her potential
and through us she's found a way to feel
out her potential much faster
than any previous system has ever been
able to accomplish
so back around 1800
super-sized surprises has happened at
the rate of one every 100 years
um massive technological revolutions
happened at the rate of less than one
every 100 years
and all of a sudden in 1800 things
accelerated
and whole new technologies began to come
into existence
every 15 years um
there was the telegraph there was
the railroad these two things alone
utterly changed the way we see ourselves
on this planet because up until then our
effective range of conversation
had been 20 miles um it was 20 miles
because people used to go out on a
sunday and walk 40 miles in those days
20 miles out and 20 miles back as hard
as that is to believe
um
just for pleasure but all of a sudden
these that were far far apart
the railroad um an expert said sorry
howard
um you froze for a few seconds here can
you
repeat the last 10 seconds or so okay so
the railroad
uh for the telegraph once there was were
trans uh transcontinental and
trans-oceanic tables
made it possible for you to communicate
with people thousands
of miles away um
experts said when the idea of railroads
were first being floated
that humans could not possibly possibly
travel at a speed greater than 11 miles
an hour
if you try to get humans traveling at 20
miles an hour the wind would suck the
breath
out of your lungs and would kill you um
that did not exactly prove to be right
um what's his name scott's
walter scott you know the famous
novelist
said there is there will never be a way
in which you can use
steam engines for a locomotion never
and yet somebody managed to take a steam
engine which tended to be the size of a
small building
turned it on its side put wheels on it
and all of a sudden you had the
locomotive so
people like uh herbert spencer and his
friends uh john stuart mill
um and his and the woman who really
wanted him more than anything
anything else in life uh a woman uh
who would give herself the pen name of
george eliot
these people could get on a train on a
sunday
travel 40 miles and then walk
in that neighborhood 40 miles distant
from them
this changed the relationship between
humans and their sense of
a planet dramatically
now we have those changes every five
years
and remember the second rule of science
look at things right
under your nose as if you have never
seen them before and then proceed from
there
look for the things that are invisible
to you the things that you and everybody
around you take for granted
and then proceed from there these
massive
what what um ray kurzweil
would caused singularities are happening
every five years
and we're simply adapting as if they're
not happening
at all and they're happening with the
introduction
of things like the personal computer
in the early 1980s um the internet
which actually started in the 1970s i
got access to it in 1983 and have been
on it ever since
um the search engine
um the world wide web
all of these things wikipedia
all of these things are things we take
for granted and yet
they are changing the very nature of
what it means to be a human being
when i first met elon musk in 2005
and he had never flown anything
and the people at nasa were laughing
okay
he said when i got out of college i
asked myself
what three things would do the most to
change humanity
in my lifetime and his answer to that
question was
the internet alternative energy and
space
so he went into the internet business
and you know help build paypal
and then have it made between 800
million and a billion dollars when he
sold his share
um i skipped over number two alternative
energy
although he's been working steadily on
that for years without a lot of
publicity
and went to number three rocketry um
getting humans uh beyond the gravity
well
um what was important was the way he
phrased it
i asked what three things would do the
most to change
humanity in my lifetime
we are somehow we're like gyroscopes
a gyroscope maintains its position
no matter what you try to do to disturb
it and we have a gyroscopic
sense of what it means to be a human
being
and we absorb all of these shape shocks
all of these super-sized surprises
hitting us right and left and we
normalize them somehow
and then we sit down and we read plato
and we imagine that he had a mind
exactly like ours and that he's talking
directly to us
or saint augustine who's so contemporary
in the way he writes that it defies
belief
no they lived in an utterly different
perceptual cosmos than
we do and the cosmos we live in
contains humans like you and me who have
broken so many of nature's
rules and do it so much every day that
it utterly
defies belief for example in the morning
you wake up you swing your feet
off the bed and you put your feet on the
floor
and then you stand up um i am online
nature loves those who oppose her most
you've just said [ __ ] you to nature
nature's most basic law is gravity
then there are her laws of physics which
say if you stand a pencil on its end
it's going to fall over
and you've just done the pencil on its
end act not only have you defied gravity
by standing up instead of laying there
limpy like a jellyfish on a mattress all
day
um you you have done it with a software
system
your vestibul the vestibular part of
your brain handles balance
and manages to pull off the pencil on
its point trick
and it does it all the rest of the day
and you don't notice
how nature has made you to say [ __ ] you
to her that's how nature explores
who's her next super sized surprise but
she's achieving those every five years
now
through human technological innovation
thank you um i've got a question from
anjen
to paraphrase the grand theory is the
tendency for parts to come together
into holes that have new properties
emergence
really and everything that exists
is the furthering of this trend so why
is there a tendency towards coming
together complexity and efficiency
uh that's a very good question it's
let's go back to pythagoras have you
ever seen
pythagoras ted trap tech tractus
it's a little pyramid made of dots at
the top is one dot below that are two
dots below that or three dots below that
or four dots
and it's a total of ten dots well what
er
what pythagoras is saying is the
universe begins as a one
and it does it begins not just with
nothingness it begins with a sheet of
space
time and speed and then it
individuates into two
and then it individually
further and i don't remember what three
means probably groups as opposed to
pairs
one way or the other this cosmos if our
theories of the big bang
are correct started as a singularity
a singleness um that differentiated into
spacetime and speed
giant super-sized surprises if you and i
had been sitting at a coffee table
before the beginning of the universe
and you had predicted that a dot
infinitely smaller than a dot
not far away from us would suddenly
burst
open like a flower and produce time
space and speed i would say you were
crazy
time is simply too bizarre a concept to
ever exist
so is space and speed
is the product of time and space
so it's totally whacked out too and all
of a sudden it would be there
and then you would make another bizarre
prediction because i'm the crusty old
fart and don't believe in these things
and you would say i predict that at any
ten to the minus three seconds of a
sliver of a second now that
spreading sheet of time space and speed
is going to precipitate the way a rain a
rain cloud precipitates and drops of
rain
and it's going to precipitate with the
very first things
and i would say you must be crazy
there are no things this place is called
a no
thing ain't nothing don't you understand
that
and how are you going to add time and
space and speed to each other
and all you gonna end up was times is
time space and speed
and i would be that wrong because there
before our eyes would be a blizzard
of quarks and then there's another
prediction
of our scientific assumptions these days
some of which are dead
wrong and it's
stochasticity randomness if a gazillion
particles were going to precipitate at
exactly the same time from exactly the
same
sheet of space time and speed they
should
have a gazillion different properties
none of them should be alike
that's a sarcastic universe that's a
random universe
but this universe is not stochastic why
because it's all been
birthed by that tiny seed at the
beginning of singularity of oneness
and it turns out there are only 16
different kinds of quarks
16 different kinds in the universe of
gazillions of identical copies of each
you must be kidding me
no this is not a monkeys of six
typewriters universe
accidentally pecking out the works of
shakespeare this is the universe
working out the implicat properties
implications
of what she's derived so far from the
first
starting rules of the cosmos in that
tiny little singularity
and those first rules probably include
things like
opposites are joined to the hip um
attraction and repulsion and
put together social groups for all your
worth because the social groups will
reveal implicat properties supersize
surprises
in ways that defy belief and define
belief as your job
as a part of those cosmos
does that all answer the question
that was amazing thank you um james cook
could you unmute yourself please
certainly thank you uh you want me to
read my question
there were just two uh basically uh two
contradictory
statements that science uh is omniscient
or will be an omniscient as the sense i
i
i understood and that we understand
science under science 101
which is kind of more something i would
be able to get behind
so which which is your belief howard my
belief is that
science contains the aspiration toward
omniscience
um omniscience is something we can chase
for the rest of our lives and never get
to
omniscience is something that the that
the human race
can continue to chase after for the next
200 generations
and never achieve because the universe
is constantly complexifying
um we are helping it do that among other
things and catching up with that
complexification process would be very
difficult but that is our mission
that is what we need to attempt so you
see that as
you see that as a singularity that we
are
trying to achieve well it's not a
singularity it's a continuous process
um but it's a continuous process we have
to throw ourselves into with all our
hearts souls and brains
so it's a destiny yeah it's a destiny
it's a destiny is what you feel inside
of you that you make happen
not that makes you happy even though it
does drive you
okay so i mean answer to that question
well i just want to read something if i
can find it here
and not lose uh where we are here we go
i want to read you the favorite of the
epigrams that i've
written and it addresses these questions
it says since there is no god
it is our job to do his work god is not
a being
he is an aspiration a gift a vision
a goal to seek ours is the
responsibility of making a cruel
universe turn just
of turning pains to understandings and
new insights into joy
of creating ways to soar the skies for
generations yet to come
a fashioning wings with which our
children's children
shall overcome of making worlds of
fantasy
materialize as reality of mining and
transforming our greatest gifts our
passions
our imaginings our pains our
insecurities
and our lusts this is the work of deity
and deity is a power that resides in us
um are we still here yes yes god we're
still here
thank you i i'd like to read a question
from ryan campbell
when you would act as a tutor to an
artist what was the first lesson you
gave
on their timeline to start a passionate
connection to their audience group
coherence
you mentioned there was a timeline and
scale to the development of the universe
big bang particle molecules in their
properties etc
is there a similar timeline or scale to
group collective coherence or
social evolution that's a very good
question the first lesson i gave was
when
imagine you came to me as a potential
client and the first thing i said to you
was if you expect me to fashion an
artificial mask
an image and sit back like a guy in a
plaid suit
flicking his cigar and say kid with this
image i'm going to make you a star
i'm going to send you to my best
competitor if you're going to work with
me you have to understand that music is
not
an exchange of plastic pieces of plastic
it is not an exchange of money it is not
an exchange of downloads
it is a change of human soul
and if you work with me my job is going
to front g
to find the gods inside of you and what
do i mean by that
um you're on deadline to turn on an
album
you have two more songs to write you sit
down at two o'clock in the afternoon
in front of a blank computer screen or a
blank piece of paper
you know you cannot possibly write a
lyric
you wonder how you've ever been able to
write a lyric in your life
and on a reasonably good day by four
o'clock in the afternoon there's a lyric
in front of you
and on an unreasonably good day maybe
once or twice in your life
that lyric feels so perfect that it
feels it wrote itself
through you my job is to find the gods
inside of you
that wrote that lyric and you go on
stage
and you see the pupils of the audience
dilate and you see their
eyes widening you see them melting into
that amoebic blob that i talked about
before
you have an out-of-body experience that
amoeba blob reaches a tunnel of energy
out to you
fills you like a pipe goes up around
your head um
and is transmogrified and goes back
through them again
my job is to find the gods who danced
you like a marionette for 70 minutes
on stage while you were going through
that continuous feedback clue
so that is the first lesson um
and and that's what i did for my clients
the best of my abilities i've got a
whole chapter
in einstein michael jackson and me a
search for soul and power
bits of rock and roll on my failures
because i had a lot of successes but
there were a lot of things that i just
couldn't
couldn't do i couldn't comprehend i mean
for example
um kenny loggins kenny loggins is one of
the
sweetest vocalists on the face of planet
earth his
his songs and his sing are absolutely
amazing
so kenny wanted me to work with him i
got him to send me all of his lyrics
all uh his upcoming album um
everything i i went and got all the
clippings with all the interviews he'd
ever done
and i studied him for a month and he was
a puzzle to me
i could not figure out what the hell was
going on in the lyrics to his upcoming
album
and then one day it hit me and i
rearranged those lyrics like jigsaw
puzzle pieces
and had a picture of what was going on
so i headed out to santa barbara to have
brunch with uh kenny loggers
and i won't tell you the john denver
adventure
that i had on the way but at any rate um
i got there and i said kenny it looks to
me in these lyrics as if there's a woman
who towers over you like a giant who
threatens
the annihilation of your individuality
and you want to get into the fastest car
you can possibly find preferably a
lamborghini
and leave this tournament at the rate of
200 miles an hour
and kenny's face went through something
strange his jaw
dropped and he got angry
and he said who the hell has been
telling you
about my marriage so
i could not talk about the gods inside
that were speaking through
kenny logan's lyrics because
they were intruding on a personal space
so my technique did not always
work um but that was lesson number one
anyway wonderful
uh dp do you have a question
yeah can you hear me yes yep
uh so my question i'm curious what you
think um
like what does it say about uh the
universe
that it should be one that happens to
value
the creation of uh super-sized surprises
well i haven't thought of it that way
because i've imagined that every
universe values the creation of
super-sized surprises but
you know um lee slack
is that his name um he's a uh
there is an astronomer at the
perimeter institute in canada who has
written about the evolution of cosmos
and says there are special things about
this cosmos
in its competition with other cosmoses
um
and if indeed there are different
qualities
to different cosmoses a cosmos that um
values super-sized surprises in fact
that is driven inevitably toward them
just can't stop herself from producing
them as god i would think a competitive
edge if it's in a world of other
cosmoses
all right i think we have time for just
one more
question um keith are you there
yeah um it's great to be here uh
so uh howard i'm wondering uh
what you make of the problem of dualism
and i've thrown in some other things i'm
really
curious um about then yeah i really
liked your book
uh global brain and um
and i majored in neuroscience myself and
i so i've been thinking a lot about the
nature of consciousness and how it
relates to physical reality
um so i'm kind of wondering uh if
anything like resulting in monism
and you mentioned bertrand russell
earlier or uh noni's
integrated information theory is on your
map or just like what your general
reflections are there and then the last
piece i want to throw in just based on
what you just said
was um uh whether or not there
is kind of an observer effect or um
where
universes that have this property of
being able to
create new um yeah
basically creating uh you know an
emerging properties of
a universe are more likely to create
consciousness and therefore be conscious
of themselves
so well that's uh we could do a whole
night on that
um dualism dualism is one of the
properties of the cosmos it just doesn't
show up between
democratic and republican parties in
north america and things like that
it's there from the very get-go and you
know one of the primary
rules of the grand unified theory is
opposites are joined to the hip so we
tend to regard two
things as opposites when in reality you
know how a curtain rod
has a big ball on one end a big
decorative ball and a big decorative
ball on the other
but they're joined by the rod in between
that's how opposites are
i mean just the molecule that makes
um oh god i'm trying to think of uh
what tends to happen is if you have
molecules that have opposite impacts
like one is a vasoconstrictor and one is
a vasodilator
they tend to come from the same parent
molecule
they are different ends of the very same
parent molecule um think about
sharingtonian behavior um it's not
talked about much these days at all
but sharingtonian behavior in
neuroscience is you've got a system
it has an exciter and it has
an inhibitor and the maintaining the
balance between these two
is excruciatingly important when you
hear
a loud bang out on the street that you
don't expect
if you watch carefully when you're
having that experience
you've got a sharing newtonian system
with an exciter and an inhibitor
and that that works like uh a
what do they call those dials on
automobiles that give you the rpm
um but it has a red zone it has a green
zone
so at any rate all of a sudden you go
over into the red zone of stress because
you have no idea what the sound is
once you are whatever you call your mind
consults its uh
conscious centers and comes up with the
notion that this is just a motorcycle
um making a a a big burp a banging burp
then all of a sudden that that thing
goes
back up into the middle zone
again and it's all because of a balance
between
um exciters and inhibitors
and there's an entire system in the body
that nobody
seems to be studying that's based on
this kind of a balance
it's the glutamate and gaba system
glutamate is the cider and gaba
is the inhibitor and i had to discover
this the hard way
because i came down with an illness that
landed me in bed
for five for 15 years and too weak to
talk
or to have another person in the room
with me for five
and what i discovered was that this i
call it a stress handling system
with yabba on one side and glutamate on
the other
was way out of whack and my body was
constantly in the very
very end of the end zone because it had
no inhibitors
so first i discovered that one thing
that could help me enormously was valium
and i could take as many as 27 valium in
a day and it would just make me a little
bit more normal
then i discovered oxytocin
well it turns out that oxytocin and
valium
both go to the gaba system the inhibitor
side
and then i discovered gabapentin and
gabapentin is
i take 30 things today because i've been
healthy as a horse since 2005
and i've been out of bed but without the
gabapentin if i forget my gabapentin in
the afternoon
i begin to show chronic fatigue syndrome
systems are
symptoms within about five hours um
and all of this is based on dualities
dualities are one of the most fruitful
things the universe has ever existed
it has has ever come up with um
a an electron has a
negative charge or a positive i can't
remember it's mixed up
one of them has one kind of
electromagnetic charge the
the uh proton has the other kind of
electromagnetic
charge they have opposite charges you
put them together
and you get all of those amazing
properties
of hydrogen which were
utterly inconceivable on the basis of
simply knowing what an electron is all
about and what a proton is all about
so put put opposites together and
sometimes if they're the right opposites
you get a super size surprise
well i can have
sadly we have come to the end of our
time
and i want to thank you so much howard
and on behalf of the stoa i have to ask
if you'd be
willing to come back and give us some
more
and knowledge oh yes yeah absolutely
i've got um
if you find this amalgam of scientific
thinking
with the arts the humanities and
especially the human spirit
interesting then well any of my books
will do but
uh einstein michael jackson and the
search for soul and the power pits of
rock and roll
is is a very very good place to to start
great thank you so much i'd love to come
back
this has been great so um we've got some
great sessions coming up tomorrow on the
stoa i see that
um the philosopher queens are returning
tomorrow we got the hollow with bonita
roy
and what gets left behind in the
hallways of hallways with nora bateson
uh check the website i dropped links in
the chat and if you'd like to support us
we're on patreon
and we'll end it here thank you everyone
so much for coming tonight
and hope to see you next time and tell
nora i said hello
well dear you should come yourself you
can tell he's interested
right okay have a good night all
right howard if we have questions do you
have an email or something like that
it's howl like wolves howling at the
moon
bloom the lom all one word howlbloom
aol.com
thank you okay have a great night